Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, today's דף Daf is זיין,
Zayin, but we pick up on ו׳ עמוד ב׳, Vav Amud Bet,
so let's get moving.
Okay, משנה, Mishnah, top of ו׳ עמוד ב׳. Vav Amud Bet. So
we discussed yesterday, right, what happens if somebody had put aside extra
money
and is it for the שקל, Shekel, is it a mistake and
it's not קדוש Kadosh or it isn't a mistake, or it doesn't
matter that it's a mistake and it is קדוש? Kadosh? And if
it's קדוש Kadosh and it's extra,
then it said it goes לנדבה. Linedavah. נדבה Nedavah means a free
will but technically means that it's going to be used in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for bringing עולות Olahs when the מזבח Mizbeach
is, you know, sort of not so active. So this משנה Mishnah
then turns to the question of general issue about when you have
leftover moneys that were sanctified and set aside for a certain קרבן,
Korban, what do you do with them? So let's take a look.
משנה: Mishnah: מותר שקלים חולין, Mosar Shekalim Chullin, leftover money for a
שקל Shekel is חולין, Chullin, that's the position of בית הלל Beis
Hillel that if you were putting your, if you were putting in
money then since there's a fixed amount for a שקל, Shekel, anything
extra was unintentional, was a טעות To'os and therefore is חולין. Chullin.
מותר עשירית האיפה, Mosar Asirit Ha'eifah, you put aside money for bringing
a tenth of an איפה Ephah for like a מנחה Minchah or
a קרבן Korban of, actually not a מנחה, Minchah, we're going to
see it's a חטאת, Chatas, one of the types of a
חטאת עולה ויורד, Chatas Olah Veyored, a חטאת Chatas that has a
varying type of קרבן Korban you can bring, amount that you bring,
whether it's a bird, whether it's a מנחה, Minchah, whether it's a
larger animal based on your wealth. That's a very specific narrow category
of חטאת Chatas for certain things. So the smallest thing you can
bring is a tenth of an איפה. Ephah. So that if you
have leftover funds for that, which is a type of a leftover
funds for חטאת, Chatas, or מותר קיני זבים וקיני זבות, Mosar Kinei
Zavim Vekinei Zavot, or birds for זב Zav and a זבה, Zavah,
which is, which is also at least one of them is a
חטאת, Chatas,
וקיני יולדות, Vekinei Yolodot, or a woman who has given birth, חטאות
ואשמות, Chatot Veashamot, or leftover money for חטאת Chatas and אשם, Asham,
מותרן נדבה. Mosran Nedavah.
So this is the general rule for any leftover money for a
חטאת Chatas or anything similar to a חטאת Chatas like an אשם
Asham or this עשירית האיפה Asirit Ha'eifah that any leftover funds, you
can't use it for another חטאת, Chatas, it's specific to this one,
so the הלכה Halachah is and assumed it's all הלכה למשה מסיני
Halachah Lemoshe Misinai that the הלכה Halachah is that it goes for
this free will for this עולה Olah for קיץ המזבח. Kaitz Hamizbeach.
Okay, זה הכלל, Zeh Haklal, one minute, כל שבא לשם חטאת ומשום
אשמה, Kol Sheba Leshem Chatat Umishum Ashmah, anything that's coming for חטאת
Chatas and for an אשם, Asham, מותרן נדבה Mosran Nedavah the leftover
money is a נדבה. Nedavah. Now again, it is worth mentioning that,
you know, that not all of this is a חטאת, Chatas, like
if you just look for example the יולדת Yoledes case, I mean
it's coming for here just תזריע, Tazria,
just easy one to jump to, right it says
they're obligatory, right, וביום שמונת טהרה לבן או לבת תביא כבש בן
שנתו לעולה ובן יונה או תור לחטאת. Vebiyom Shemonat Toharoh Laven O
Lebas Tavi Keves Ben Shenato Leolah Uven Yonah O Tor Lechatat. So
the כבש Keves is לעולה Leolah and the בן יונה Ben Yonah
or the תור Tor is לחטאת. Lechatat. So presumably when it says
קיני יולדות Kinei Yolodot it's talking just about the birds which are
the חטאת Chatas part of that. Yes, what do you do,
these are not things you bring voluntary?
No, well that is true but they're עולות Olahs as well, but
the end of the משנה Mishnah doesn't emphasize what's obligatory, it ends
with the חטאת Chatas point. Rabbi Dov what did you want to
say?
Can I say a Hebrew point that קיני זבים וקיני זבות, Kinei
Zavim Vezavot, that word is from the nest?
Yeah, קן, Kan, קן Kan is the nest meaning birds. Shows קן
ציפור. Kan Tzipor.
Yeah, it means birds, right, exactly. So yeah,
so just one second I'm just quickly look up one other thing
here.
One
minute, what
else okay.
Yeah, so for example if you look at like the זבה, Zavah,
it's וביום השמיני תקח לה שתי תורים או שני בני יונה והביאה
אותם אל הכהן ועשה הכהן את האחד חטאת ואת האחד עולה. Ubeyom
Hashemini Tikach Lah Shte Torim O Shne Bne Yonah Vehavem El Hakohen,
Veasah Hakohen Et Ha'echad Chatat Veet Ha'echad Olah. So when it says
קיני זבים וקיני זבות, Kinei Zavim Vezavot, right, two birds, you know,
that could include also the עולה, Olah, so then it's interesting and
we'll see a little bit of this in the גמרא, Gemara, when
you have like a packaged deal, when you have like both birds,
one is a חטאת Chatas one is an עולה, Olah, what is
the, how do you treat do you treat that money as, you
know, as one package or do you divide it? So the simple
sense of the משנה Mishnah is that since fund- there is a
חטאת Chatas there and we could also say fundamentally both birds are
being brought for a טהרה Taharah process. חטאת Chatas does not just
mean sin, חטאת Chatas particularly in the context of זב, Zav, זבה,
Zavah, and יולדת Yoledes also means purification, so that that's treated with
this הלכה Halachah that the leftover is for a נדבה. Nedavah. Anyway
just pointed out because although there is a חטאת Chatas there, not
both birds are a חטאת. Chatas. And now we look about what's
left- the story is with leftover for an
עולה. Olah. מותר עולה לעולה, Mosar Olah Leolah, leftover money for an
עולה Olah is for an עולה. Olah. Now the difference by saying
עולה Olah and נדבה Nedavah is נדבה Nedavah is communal funds which
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash uses to bring for an עולה Olah
when the when the altar is not busy, whereas an עולה Olah
means if you set aside money for your personal עולה Olah and
you have leftover, it's for an עולה. Olah. save it up. An
עולה olah is a free will sacrifice, save up that money and
use it next time you want to bring another עולה. olah. מותר
מנחה למנחה, Moisar minchah l'minchah, similarly if you set aside money for
a מנחה minchah and you have leftover, fine, put it aside. Next
time you want to bring a מנחה minchah you can draw on
those funds. That is a personal free-will sacrifice. It is not obligatory
and sin-related like the חטאת chatas or purification-related. And therefore this you
get to hold on to the money, not that it's חולין, chullin,
you hold on to it and you use it next time you
have a similar use.
Similarly, מותר שלמים שלמים, Moisar shelamim shelamim, leftover money for a שלמים
shelamim goes for another שלמים, shelamim, for yourself next time you want
to bring a שלמים. shelamim. מותר הפסח, Moisar hapesach, leftover money for
a קרבן פסח, korban pesach, לשלמים, lishlamim, goes for a שלמים, shelamim,
which is interesting, right? Because you could have said, why not I
just save that money and use that money for next פסח? pesach?
But this gets us back to everything we learned in מסכת פסחים,
Masechet Psachim, this idea that after פסח pesach the, if you actually
have the animal that's left over or money, it converts its status
to a
שלמים. shelamim. מותר נזירים לנזירים, Moisar nezirim l'nezirim, if you have money
that is for נזירים, nezirim, multiple נזירים, nezirim, meaning somehow there's a
communal collection, I one has to try to imagine what the sociological
phenomenon was that there were a lot of נזירים nezirim in your
community and they all needed to bring קרבנות korbanos and they didn't
necessarily have the money for it. So you raised up, because the
נזירות neziros was over, you raised funds for the נזירים, nezirim, you
had a special נזירים nezirim charity. That then if there's leftover, you
save, hold on to it for the next נזיר, nazir, because it's
not specific to a particular נזיר nazir and therefore it can be
used for the next one. However,
no, מותר נזיר לנדבה, Moisar nazir lindavah, however if you're an individual
נזיר nazir and you set aside money for your קרבן, korban, then
it's similar to the beginning of the משנה mishnah where if obligatory
sacrifice, as some type of a קרבן korban that's brought, purification or
it's not exactly purification but to change a status to end a
period, in that type of a situation you do not use it
for the next one, that's נזיר nazir very specific for the one
you're in, like the חטאת, chatas, and the leftover money would actually
go for נדבה, nedavah, which is similar to the ruling of the
חטאת. chatas. Okay, so let's take a look now at the גמרא.
Gemara.
אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, said רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, עד
דאנן תמן, Ad d'anan taman, while I was still there, which is
where? There's understood to be בבל. Bavel. So it's quite interesting, right,
when you know in the בבלי Bavli you get a lot of
going to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, here you get a lot, here
you get references of being in בבל. Bavel. So when I was
still there in בבל, Bavel, שמיע קל רב יהודה שאיל לשמואל, shami'a
kal Rav Yehuda sha'il l'Shmuel, I heard the voice of רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda asking שמואל. Shmuel. Very interesting, right, graphic, you know, almost
graphic way. He didn't just say, oh I heard that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda asked שמואל. Shmuel. I heard the voice of רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda asking, maybe he was asking from behind a curtain, I
don't know. Anyway, no, but שמיע קל רב יהודה שאיל לשמואל, shami'a
kal Rav Yehuda sha'il l'Shmuel, I heard רב יהודה Rav Yehuda asking
שמואל Shmuel the following question. הפריש שקלו ומת, Hefrish shiklo umess,
somebody set aside their שקל, shekel, they sanctified their שקל shekel and
then they died. So what do you do with the money? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so that was the question. So that's sort of
like a מותר שקלים, moisar shekalim, leftover money for a שקל. shekel.
אמר ליה יפלו לנדבה, Amar lei yiplu lindavah, that goes to a
נדבה. nedavah. Now even though our משנה mishnah says מותר שקלים חולין,
moisar shekalim chullin, that's when, remember, you were putting aside pennies and
you weren't aware that you had actually already hit a half שקל,
shekel, so the rest was considered הקדש טעות. hekdesh ta'us. This is
not הקדש טעות. hekdesh ta'us. This is you are sanctified, the guy
sanctified it properly then he just died. So what do you do?
So if you remember from the last משנה, mishnah, we said that
when actually something is sanctified legitimately as a שקל shekel and, you
know, for example בית שמאי Beis Shammai they don't buy into this
whole idea of טעות, ta'us, and the money is leftover, it goes
לנדבה. lindavah. So the same ruling is here, that leftover for a
שקל shekel goes for נדבה nedavah when you do not have the
טעות ta'us element. Yes?
Is this רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi actually רב
יוסף Rav Yosef
who was blind?
Oh, that's interesting. That's an interesting question. רב יוסף Rav Yosef is
רבי יוסי?
Rabbi Yosi? Yeah. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in the משנה mishnah is
a תנא? Tanna?
No, no, no, it's not a תנא, Tanna, it's an אמורא, Amora,
right. Yeah, I don't know. That's a good question. I don't know
the matching up of the ways the אמוראים Amoraim are referred to
in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi because obviously sometimes the names get converted, change
a little bit. Yeah, it's an interesting question. Maybe that's why he
said this voice of. Exactly, that's an interesting speculation. I don't know.
Yes. Just a quick קרבן korban clarification. I bring an עולה olah
or I bring a שלמים, shelamim, is my כוונה kavanah different?
You don't really need כוונה, kavanah, although the רמב"ם Rambam says that
the same way there's an idea of saying a וידוי vidui on
a חטאת, chatas, the רמב"ם—I Rambam don't know if he has a
source, but anyway—speculates that you would actually say like דברי שבח divrei
shevach over a שלמים, shelamim, you would sort of also do some
type of a, you know, of a ritual to give it context
and meaning and so on.
והעולה נמי מכפרת. v'ha'olah nami mechaperes. Right.
The עולה olah is supposed to be מכפר על עשה. mechaper al
asei. How you exactly conceptualize it. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't talk,
look, that's a very, you know, sort of like significant about the
whole shift from קרבנות korbanos to תפילה tefillah is the issue of
כוונה kavanah versus an external type of an act that, you know,
that is that is seen as sort of being, you know, effectual.
Okay, so now it says like this. מותר עשירית האיפה שלו. Moisar
asiris ha'eifah shelo. Now... What do you do with leftover money of
the עשירית האיפה Asirit HaEphah of his? Now who's the his? What's
that pronoun about? So we're going to see that what it means
is it's assuming we're talking about a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, שלו,
shelo, the one person who brings a regular עשירית האיפה. Asirit HaEphah.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings an עשירית האיפה Asirit HaEphah every
day, half in the morning and half in the afternoon as a
מנחה. Minchah. So that's a חובה, chovah, that's an obligatory sacrifice, and
that's different from the משנה Mishnah which is talking about an עשירית
האיפה Asirit HaEphah of a חטאת Chatat when there's an עולה ויורד.
Oleh V'Yored. So but it's not necessarily clear at the outset. So
let's take a look. What do you have leftover money from that?
רבי יוחנן אמר יוליכם לים המלח, Rabbi Yochanan amar yolichem l'Yam HaMelach,
you throw them into the Dead Sea. There you can't do anything
with them. אבל רבי אליעזר אמר יפלו לנדבה. Aval Rabbi Eliezer amar
yiplu l'nedavah. No, you use it for the נדבה, nedavah, for the,
you know, for the בית המ- Beit Ham- for the מזבח mizbeach
when it's not busy. So the גמרא Gemara says מתניתין פליגא על
רבי יוחנן. matnitin peligah al Rabbi Yochanan. Our משנה Mishnah directly contradicts
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. מותר שקלים חולין מותר עשירית האיפה מותר קיני
זבים לזב קיני זבות מותר קיני יולדות וחטאת ואשמות מותר נדבה. Motar
shekalim chullin, motar asirit haephah, motar kinei zavim l'zav, kinei zavot, motar
kinei yoldot v'chatat v'ashamot motar nedavah. Our משנה Mishnah says that leftover
money from the עשירית האיפה Asirit HaEphah is a נדבה. nedavah. How
did he say throw them into the Dead Sea? So מה עביד
ליה רבי יוחנן, ma avid leh Rabbi Yochanan, what does רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan do with our משנה? Mishnah? פתר לה, Patar lah, he
explains it: מותר עשירית האיפה שמנחת חוטא של כל ישראל. Motar asirit
haephah sheminkhat choteh shel kol Yisrael. Our משנה Mishnah is talking about
the עשירית האיפה Asirit HaEphah of a, of a מנחת חוטא minchat
choteh again. A normal חטאת chatat has to be an animal, has
to be a sheep or whatever, but, but if you are very
specific number of sins like five types of sins mentioned at the
end of פרשת ויקרא Parshat Vayikra that are in this category of
עולה ויורד, Oleh V'Yored, that if you don't have the funds for
it you can bring a lesser קרבן, korban, and one of them
would be, and therefore the lowest of that would be the עשירית
האיפה, Asirit HaEphah, this מנחה minchah which serves as a sin offering.
That's our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah is talking about a type
of a חטאת chatat substitute for a חטאת. chatat. But what the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings as an עשירית האיפה, Asirit HaEphah, that's
an obligatory מנחה minchah which is not a חטאת. chatat. Now again
this raises the question: when we say if you can't use the
funds they go for נדבה nedavah by the חטאת, chatat, presumably the
explanation for that, the easiest explanation for that is something that's obligatory,
that's designated for a particular obligation, and then there was leftover funds,
you can't use it for the original obligation, you can't therefore transfer
to another type of an obligation, so there there's sort of the
catch-all, the general הלכה halachah that it goes לנדבה l'nedavah to this
עולה olah on the, you know, when the מזבח mizbeach is בטל.
batel. That seems to be, it's not limited to a חטאת. chatat.
For example, as it applies to the שקל shekel when it's not
a תוס, tose, like we said before, the guy set aside the
שקל shekel and he died. It applies to a נזיר Nazir who
had leftover funds for his קרבן. korban. It applied to the birds
that a יולדת yoldet that a זבה zavah brings even though one
of them is an עולה. olah. So the logic to say that
the leftover funds for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for his מנחה,
minchah, even if it's not a חטאת, chatat, should go לנדבה l'nedavah
makes a lot of sense, and it seems that נדבה nedavah is
what you do with leftover obligatory funds. Does not seem it unique
to the idea of a חטאת. chatat. So I have to tell
you I don't understand the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that
says: well this isn't a חטאת chatat and it's obligatory so you
don't know what to do with it, so therefore you got to
just throw it out, throw to ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, dispose of
it. If that's true why don't you do the same by the
שקל? shekel? Why don't you do the same by, you know, I
don't get it. It seems that the general rule is is that
if it's obligatory and leftover it gets used לנדבה. l'nedavah.
That's a communal נדבה? nedavah?
Yes, a communal נדבה. nedavah.
So it was an individual, it's leftover from an
individual obligation, but the
כהן Kohen says to himself when he gives that נדבה... nedavah...
He doesn't say to himself, he gives it to the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, the money, and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash puts it
in its general fund that it draws on when it needs to
get more activity on the מזבח.
mizbeach. Ah, so it's not a specific, it's not transferred to a
specific קרבן. korban. Correct. Correct.
All these funds that go לנדבה l'nedavah they get given to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, they get put in this fund.
Like a slush fund?
Well yes, but it's a specific fund to be used for keeping,
keeping קרבנות korbanot being brought on the מזבח. mizbeach.
And that money was kept in one of those לשכות? lishchot?
Yes, it was kept, yeah, there was a special place
it was kept, right,
or a box, yeah, a שופר. shofar. Yes. So anyway I don't
know the idea of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, unless again רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan makes this difference because it's a type of a not
just obligatory private קרבן, korban, which is everything we were talking about,
including the שקל, shekel, but it's sort of obligatory communal. On the
one hand it's like the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is sort of
a private individual, but on the other hand it's also about the
general things that are done in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
maybe that's why he sees this as somewhat different and actually does
not go to this נדבה nedavah rule category. Otherwise it's hard to
understand. Alright now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי יוסי
אמר על דא עליל. Rabbi Yossi amar: al da alil. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi said: on the following עליל. alil. The מפרשים mefarshim say
it means to ask. I mean an עלילה alilah is like a
complaint. I'm not exactly sure, some say the word is על al
not עליל, alil, but I didn't, I meant to check actually there's
a good Palestinian Aramaic dictionary, you
know, for the ירושלמי Yerushalmi by what's his name... But anyway, they
say the word עליה alyah here means to ask. על דא עליה
Al da alyah אבא בר בא Abba bar Ba דאינון deinun okay,
this is the following thing אבא בר בא Abba bar Ba sort
of asked or or stated. דאינון Deinun mean we say, I'm sorry,
they say, they in בבל Bavel say the following: שהם אומרים Shehem
omrim מנין שהפסח משתנה לשם שלמים? Minayin shehapesach mishtaneh l'shem shelamim? How
do you know that a פסח Pesach is going back to the
line of the משנה Mishnah that leftover funds for פסח Pesach are
used as a שלמים? Shelamim? How do you know that even the
animal that's sanctified as a פסח Pesach if it's after פסח Pesach
and you שחט shacht it, it converts to a שלמים? Shelamim? תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar the verse says: ואם מן הצאן קרבנו לזבח שלמים,
V'im min hatzon korbano l'zevach shelamim, if it's a sheep and it's
being brought as a שלמים, Shelamim, that's the פסוק Pasuk in the
beginning of ויקרא Vayikra that tells you how to offer a שלמים.
Shelamim. So the דרשה Derasha that they make in בבל Bavel is
the following way: כל שהוא מן הצאן בא שלמים. Kol shehu min
hatzon ba shelamim. Anything that ואם מן הצאן, V'im min hatzon, any
קרבן Korban that's a sheep קרבן, Korban, if you don't use it
for the right thing, if you didn't use it for its original
purpose, it's מן ה...... min ha... it's זבח שלמים, zevach shelamim, it
becomes a שלמים. Shelamim.
So he answers, yes!
Except it's a little bit too inclusive, which is what his question
is. התבון? Hatavun? So this is what... so this is what he
asked. So it says that, you know, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei said
that רב אבא בר בא Rav Abba bar Ba asked. So this
is... so in בבל Bavel they made this דרשה, Derasha, so רב
אבא בר בא Rav Abba bar Ba challenged this. התבון? Hatavun? Is
this really true, correct? היציבון? Hayatzivun? הרי עולה מן הצאן? Harei olah
min hatzon? How about an עולה? Olah? That comes from sheep. So
דבר שאינו בא אלא מן הצאן, Davar she'eino ba ela min hatzon,
so... so... I'm sorry, הרי עולה, Harei olah, I'm sorry, put the
comma in the wrong place, הרי עולה. Harei olah. I'm sorry, put
the comma in the wrong place. How about an עולה? Olah? That
comes from sheep. So why don't we say leftover of an עולה
Olah comes as a שלמים? Shelamim? And we don't, we say it's
an עולה. Olah. So the answer is, no. מן הצאן, Min hatzon,
being מן הצאן, Min hatzon, דבר שאינו בא אלא מן הצאן, Davar
she'eino ba ela min hatzon, something that only comes from sheep, יצאת
עולה שהיא באה אף מן הבקר. Yatzat olah shehi ba'ah af min
habakar. It does... so an עולה Olah would not be included in
that... in that because an עולה Olah can come from cattle. So
ואם מן הצאן V'im min hatzon includes פסח Pesach that only comes
from sheep, but does not include עולה Olah that can come from
things other than sheep. But we're not... we're still not done. היציבון?
Hayatzivun? Is this still correct? הרי אשם? Harei asham? How about an
אשם? Asham? That only comes from a sheep. Comes from... from a
male sheep, a ram, but it only comes from a sheep. So
maybe if you leftover money from an אשם Asham should be used
as a שלמים. Shelamim. Maybe that's in the פסוק Pasuk as well.
So אמר רב בון בר כהנא, Amar Rav Bun bar Kahana, no.
מן הצאן, Min hatzon, דבר שהוא בא מכל הצאן. Davar shehu ba
mikol hatzon. יצאת...... Yatzat...
I'm sorry, מכל הצאן mikol hatzon he said. יצא אשם שאינו בא
אלא מן האילים בלבד. Yatza asham she'eino ba ela min ha'eylim bilvad.
No, צאן Tzon means all type of flocks. צאן Tzon doesn't just
mean sheep. Flocks includes sheep and goats. So a שלמים Shelamim can
come from sheep and goats and a פסח Pesach can come from
sheep and goats. But an אשם Asham can only come from male
sheep, from rams. It cannot come from goat. A פסח Pesach also
can only be male, but an אשם Asham can only come from
sheep and cannot come from ram... from goats. So יצא אשם, Yatza
asham, it excludes אשם Asham שאינו בא אלא מן האילים בלבד, she'eino
ba ela min ha'eylim bilvad, only comes from rams. Again, not meant
to emphasize the male part, meant to emphasize not goats. So ואם
מן הצאן, V'im min hatzon, something that could come from all types
of flocks, sheep and goats, a פסח, Pesach, if you don't use
it for a פסח, Pesach, you use it for a שלמים. Shelamim.
So we've excluded an אשם, Asham, which is only from sheep and
not goats. We've excluded certainly an עולה, Olah, which is even from
cattle. So we have the פסוק Pasuk telling us about a פסח.
Pesach. But we're still not done. So the גמרא Gemara points out...
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: שבכל אתר Sheb'chol atar in
all places את אמר at amar מן min למעט. l'ma'et. You say
when it says מן min something, it doesn't mean the whole category,
it means a subset, from.
וכאן את מר V'chan at mar and here you're saying... את אומר
at omer מן min לרבות? l'rabot? That מן min is inclusive? מן
הצאן Min hatzon means all types of flocks, sheep and goats? מן
min usually means a subset. So how can you say מן min
is coming to emphasize both sheep and goats? So אמר רב מנא
Amar Rav Mana הכי נמי hachi nami מן min למעט. l'ma'et. Yes,
מן min is excluding some types of sheep. מיעט שאינו בא בן
שתי שנים. Mi'et she'eino ba ben shtei shanim.
It excludes sheep that, you know, two years old, right? A פסח
Pesach can only be one year old. מיעט שאינו בא נקבה. Mi'et
she'eino ba nekevah. It excludes females. A פסח Pesach can only be
males. Of course a שלמים Shelamim can be females, but a פסח
Pesach can only be males. Okay, so the מן הצאן min hatzon
means some type of a thing that comes from a subset of
the sheep, not all sheep, not the females, not the ones that
are two years old. So it would be the פסח. Pesach. But
צאן Tzon still means
all types of
sheep, means both sheep and goat, and therefore to exclude an אשם.
Asham. And מן min to exclude things that are two years old
or female, and therefore to focus us on the פסח. Pesach. So
the גמרא Gemara now points out: וגבי אשם נמי מן למעט הוא
שאינו בא אלא מן האילים. V'gabei asham nami min l'ma'et hu she'eino
ba ela min ha'eylim. And sort of it's not exactly clear, this
may be a response back and saying: okay, then why not say
that the מן min works for the אשם Asham as well and
it's coming to exclude... you know, and it's coming to say only
sheep and not goats. All right, so basically it's... we sort of
have an answer, we sort of don't. Okay, again, the
דרשה derasha is, right, the... It doesn't include an אשם asham because
an אשם asham doesn't come from all צאן. tzon. It comes only
from sheep, not from goats. What about the מן? min? The מן
min is not meant
to say sheep not goats, it's meant to say one year and
male, some type of the flock. Okay, and therefore but we still
are going to exclude an אשם asham because we're still going to
say that צאן tzon means all types of meaning both sheep and
goats. מן min means about age and gender, but צאן tzon includes
both sheep and goats and therefore excludes an אשם, asham, even though
even though the גמרא Gemara says at the end that in theory
you could have said מן min is meant to say only sheep
and not goats and therefore talking about an אשם, asham, but we
are choosing not to read it that way and therefore talking about
a פסח Pesach and not talking about an
אשם. asham. Yes, Rabbi Dov?
היטיבון? haitivun? היטיבון haitivun is like מיתיבי? maitivei?
I'm not
sure. It means, yes,
it means is this really correct? So I was thinking it, I
haven't, it does mean like is this really correct don't we say
etc. I'm not sure, I didn't actually look at the exact
translation. I was wondering if הישיבון hayeshivun means like from will this
really be established from like ישב. yashev. How do they translate the
word הישיבון? hayeshivun? I mean I know it's like an interrogative challenge
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, I just don't know the exact translation of
the word. Do you see it there? What do they translate the
word? Doesn't say? לשון השבה? lashon hashavah?
Yeah. I mean מיתיבי maitivei is let me respond, right, but anyway,
yeah.
So I was thinking before what you עליל, alil, from עלילה, alilah,
right? I said that.
I thought you said that
I said עלילה.
alilah. Okay. You weren't listening, you were too busy looking at your
English. I said that עליל alil comes from עלילה. alilah.
I thought maybe you only suggested it. It does.
Right, so the offering suggests a challenge from some type of a
textual source. Okay. Right. Yes.
The interchangeable the money and the animal itself
as.
When we're talking about the פסח, Pesach, yes. פסח Pesach both animal
changes to a שלמים shlamim and the money changes to a שלמים
shlamim if you have leftover. Yes, both are true. Okay. So it
says like this.
But what did it say there for the word הישיבון? hayeshivun? Take
can I take a look?
היטיבון? haitivun? It was היטיבון haitivun was the way they.
Yeah, but what does it mean?
It says raise an objection.
So it's like מיתיבי, maitivei, yeah, that's what I thought. Okay.
But עלילה alilah is not a question, it's more of an objection,
right? It's about עלילה עלינו, alilah aleinu, that's what I was getting.
Yeah. You said it was a question but I'd say more of
an objection.
Right. Okay, you're right, meaning not a question like looking for information,
right, a question like a challenge. A challenge. Yeah. Okay.
All right, so now we get how they get this דרשה drasha
and how they limit it to a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues like this.
Where were
we?
Okay.
היטיבון, haitivun, is this really true? והכתיב ואם מן הצאן קרבנו מן
הכבשים או מן העזים לעולה. ve'haktiv ve'im min hatzon korbano min haksavim
o min ha'izim l'olah. You have the same פסוק ואם מן הצאן
pasuk ve'im min hatzon by שלמים shlamim and by an עולה. olah.
So if ואם מן הצאן ve'im min hatzon means something that comes
from sheep and meaning all sheep sheep and goats or whatever anyway
and it means a פסח Pesach and we use it to say
that a פסח Pesach will become a שלמים, shlamim, let's read from
this פסוק pasuk and say ואם מן הצאן ve'im min hatzon means
a פסח Pesach and if it's not a פסח Pesach it'll become
an עולה. olah. מן הכבשים או מן העזים לעולה? min haksavim o
min ha'izim l'olah? מעתה me'ata why don't we say מותר פסח בעולה?
motar Pesach b'olah? Leftover money from the פסח Pesach will be brought
as an עולה? olah? So אמר רבי אבון משנים דבר שהוא לאכילה
לדבר שהוא לאכילה. amar Rabbi Avun meshanim davar shehu l'achila l'davar shehu
l'achila. ואין משנים דבר שהוא לאכילה לדבר שאינו לאכילה. ve'ein meshanim davar
shehu l'achila l'davar she'eino l'achila.
It's very easy. If we can read the פסח Pesach into one
of these two פרשיות, parashiyot, either the שלמים shlamim or the עולה,
olah, we'll read it into the שלמים shlamim פרשה parasha because you
eat a פסח, Pesach, you eat a שלמים. shlamim. We won't read
it into the עולה olah פרשה parasha just to say that something
that started off as something that could be eaten would become an
עולה olah and not be able to be eaten. אמר רבי יוסי
בר אבון משנים קדשים קלים לשם קדשים קלים. amar Rabbi Yose bar
Abun meshanim kodashim kalim l'shem kodashim kalim. ואין משנים קדשים קלים לשם
קדשי קדשים. ve'ein meshanim kodashim kalim l'shem kodashei kodashim. Another good answer.
We'd rather a פסח Pesach convert to a שלמים, shlamim, they're both
קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, than a פסח Pesach convert to an עולה.
olah. פסח Pesach is קדשים קלים kodashim kalim and an עולה olah
is קדשי קדשים. kodashei kodashim. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר. Rabbi Yochanan amar.
Okay, fine. So by the way, what's fascinating here is it shows
you the intersection or the interaction, I should say, of סברא sevara
with a דרשה, drasha, right? Because normally we'd say oh, it's a
דרשה, drasha, it's a פסוק, pasuk, like it's automatic, it's like mechanical
almost. This is the דרשה, drasha, this is the פסוק, pasuk, this
is the conclusion. But you often have a lot of choices how
to read the פסוק, pasuk, what types of which פסוק pasuk to
read. We could have read it that a פסח Pesach becomes an
עולה, olah, but no, it makes more sense to say a פסח
Pesach becomes a שלמים, shlamim, so we'll read it into that פסוק
pasuk and not this, but look, the גמרא Gemara said it before,
we could have also read the פסוק pasuk to say an אשם
asham becomes a שלמים, shlamim, but we chose to read the פסוק
pasuk that the פסוק pasuk is excluding אשם asham and including and
including a פסח. Pesach. So it really shows you like the type
of I
mean, it's the
גמרא. Gemara.
It's not obvious that you could take an offering and raise
its and
elevate its status. You could, but if you have a choice between
saying it converts to something similar as opposed to converts to something
different, we'd rather say it converts to something similar.
That's a choice, exactly. That's a סברא. sevara. That's a סברא.
sevara. Right. Right. I get it. Right. Okay. All right. So now
the רישא resha goes like this: על דא עליה רבי חנינה דאינון
אמרין, Al da olye Rabbi Chanina de-inun amrin, on the following thing
רבי חנינה Rabbi Chanina challenged, דאינון אמרין de-inun amrin again, they say
in בבל, Bavel, אין הפסח משתנה לשם שלמים אלא אם כן שחטו
לשם שלמים. Ein haPesach mishtaneh l'shem shelamim ela im ken shechato l'shem
shelamim. Now this is again,
we learned this in the בבלי Bavli by פסח, Pesach, right, when
you do change an actual animal, not just leftover money of a
פסח Pesach to a שלמים shelamim after the פסח, Pesach, you have
to שחט shecht it שלא לשמו. she-lo lishmo. You can't שחט shecht
it לשם פסח l'shem Pesach after פסח, Pesach, then it won't be
good. Now what do you have to שחט shecht it for? So
he claims, the claim here is that in בבל Bavel they said
you have to שחט shecht it specifically for שלמים shelamim for it
to convert. I will remind you that we did not say that
when we learned פסחים. Pesachim. We said any שלא לשמו she-lo lishmo
converts it to a שלמים, shelamim, but he said that in בבל
Bavel they were saying that you have to שחט shecht it specifically
for שלמים shelamim for it to convert. ואני אומר, V'ani omer, and
he says and I say, אפילו שחטו לשם עולה, afilu shechato l'shem
olah,
any other קרבן korban you שחט shecht for as long as you're
not שחטינג shechting it for a פסח, Pesach, if it's after פסח
Pesach and you שחט shecht it for another קרבן, korban, it converts
to a שלמים. shelamim. אמר רב אילא, Amar Rav Ila, says רב
אילא, Rav Ila, טעמא דרבי יוחנן, ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan, the reason רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that even if you שחט shecht it for
an עולה olah it converts to a שלמים, shelamim, אם מן הצאן
קרבנו לזבח
שלמים. im min hatzon korbano l'zevach shelamim. Again, now we're buying into
the דרשה drasha that they had in בבל. Bavel. Remember this was
a בבל Bavel דרשה. drasha. אם מן הצאן קרבנו לזבח שלמים, Im
min hatzon korbano l'zevach shelamim, something that comes from sheep, a פסח
Pesach becomes a שלמים, shelamim, כל שהוא זבח לזבח, Kol she-hu zevach
l'zevach, if you do it for any קרבן, korban, then שלמים, shelamim,
כל שהוא לזבח בא שלמים. Kol she-hu l'zevach ba shelamim. Okay, so
he doesn't have to שחט shecht for שלמים, shelamim, he just has
to שחט shecht it לזבח l'zevach for some other קרבן korban and
then it automatically becomes a שלמים. shelamim. ומשתנה, U'mishtaneh, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: what if
you שחט shecht an animal not for a זבח? zevach?
Well, you could שחט shecht maybe for a פסח Pesach purpose, for
a פסח Pesach or something. All right, anyway, maybe if you שחט
shechted it as חולין chullin it wouldn't work.
That's what I was just mentioning.
All right, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ומשתנה למחשבת
פסול. u'mishtaneh l'machshevet pasul.
Now, it changes as far as פסול מחשבה pasul machshava is concerned.
What does that mean? It means when you are שחטינג shechting it
for let's say an עולה, olah, not for a שלמים, shelamim, how
much does your thought of it as an עולה, olah, it makes
it into a שלמים, shelamim, but how much does your thought of
it as an עולה olah give it the הלכות halachos of an
עולה? olah? And even for invalidity purposes. What would be the case?
I mean it's going to be a שלמים. shelamim. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. היך עבידא? Hech abida? What would be
the case? שחטו לשם עולה, Shechato l'shem olah, let's say you שחט
shechted it for an עולה, olah, על מנת לזרוק דמה למחר, al
m'nat lizrok dama l'machar,
and you had intention for פיגול pigul thought, to throw the blood
tomorrow. So what's the הלכה? halacha? Will it be פיגול pigul or
not? So the גמרא Gemara says, who cares whether it was an
עולה olah thought or a שלמים shelamim thought? Any מחשבה תזרוק הדם
למחר machshava tizrok hadam l'machar is פיגול pigul for any קרבן. korban.
Any קרבן korban you're planning to do it tomorrow is פיגול. pigul.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מכל מקום פסול
הוא. mi-kol makom pasul hu. So what? Either way you're going to
invalidate it whether you consider it to be, whether the עולה olah
thought makes it more like an עולה olah or more like a
שלמים. shelamim.
And then everything was done
correctly besides the one thing. Ah, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara
going to answer. No, אם תימר, im teimar, אם im here means
אם, im,
if you say משתנה למחשבת פסול. mishtaneh l'machshevet pasul. Now there's a
whole question of the גירסא. girsa. I'm going to read it the
way the תפארת החדשים, Tiferet HaChadashim, who's the תלמיד talmid of the
גר"א Gra reads this. אם תימר משתנה למחשבת פסול, Im teimar mishtaneh
l'machshevet pasul,
then פסול. pasul. אם תימר אין משתנה למחשבת פסול, Im teimar ein
mishtaneh l'machshevet pasul,
then פיגול. pigul. Okay, so meaning you can make it פסול pasul
without making it פיגול. pigul. As Michael reminds us, for something to
be פיגול pigul it's very hard to be פיגול pigul because everything
else has to be done correctly. So it says like this: If
you say that the sort of עולה olah מחשבה machshava makes it,
you know, you sort of are treating it like yes it's a
שלמים shelamim but it's a שלמים shelamim that was done לשם עולה,
l'shem olah, then if you add to that a פיגול pigul thought,
that's going to, it has two problems as it were. It's got
a פיגול pigul thought, but it's also got this like עולה olah
thought going on. Although the עולה olah thought doesn't make it invalid,
somehow that's seen as a problem and not the natural way of
doing it, and therefore that will save it from being פיגול. pigul.
It will only be פסול. pasul. אבל אם תימר אין משתנה למחשבת
פסול, aval im teimar ein mishtaneh l'machshevet pasul,
if you say that you thought for an עולה olah but we
don't really sort of give that thought any weight, it's just like
a straight שחטינג shechting לשם שלמים l'shem shelamim for this, then normal
פיגול pigul will take effect and we don't give any weight to
that מחשבה machshava of an עולה olah and it doesn't make it,
you know, problematic to further save it from being פיגול. pigul. Okay,
yes.
What's the נפקא מינא *nafka mina* between being פסול *pasul* or being
פיגול *pigul*?
פיגול *Pigul* first of all you transgress when you שחט *shecht* when
you make it פיגול *pigul*. Number two is that if you eat
פיגול *pigul* you're חייב כרת *chayav kareis* for eating פיגול *pigul*. So
that's right. Those are good points. Right. Okay so let's take a
look. Let's keep on going. That was a little complicated. Now לשמו
ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo*. You know what you got to love
this. I mean I got to tell you it's like finally we're
having a סוגיא *sugya* that sounds a little bit like a בבלי
*Bavli*. You know it actually talks a little bit. It's not these
one liners. You know you get a little bit of a little
bit of elaborates. I mean okay that last line was exactly was
you know could have been fleshed out a little bit more. But
anyway it's also סוגיא *sugya* that's parallel in the בבלי *Bavli* so
I know what it's talking about. Anyway okay so it says like
this. לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo*. You שחט *shecht*-ed this פסח
*Pesach* after פסח *Pesach*. You have to שחט *shecht* it שלא לשמו
*shelo lishmo* for it to be a שלמים shelamim, *shlamim*. When you
שחט *shecht*-ed it you said הריני שוחטו לשם פסח ולשם שלמים shelamim,
*hareini shochto leshem Pesach uleshem shlamim*. So does לשם שלמים shelamim *leshem
shlamim* save it or לשם עולה olah, *leshem Olah* would it matter?
Or does לשם פסח *leshem Pesach* fix it in its old פסח
*Pesach* identity and make it פסול *pasul*? What's the הלכה halacha *halacha*?
לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo* בשאר ימות השנה *bish'ar yemot hashana*
when it's not פסח *Pesach*. רבי אבין בר בון בר חייה *Rabbi
Avin bar Bun bar Chiya* בשם שמואל Shmuel, בר אבא *beshem Shmuel
bar Abba* says the following. מכיוון שאין לו שם *mikeivan she'ein lo
shem* since this פסח *Pesach* on the rest of the year does
not have a designation, right? It's sort of seen to be sort
of non-designated. So then מנעשו כשחטו לשמו ושלא לשמו בשתיקה *minas'u kishochto
lishma u'shelo lishma bishitika*. I'm the way this is read it's not
so clear what it means but the way that some of the
מפרשים meforshim *mefarshim* read it is לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo*
kind of sort of you know neutralize one another. They they short-circuit.
Yeah. לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo* and so you wipe they
so they sort of you know they they smash together so it's
like you did it without saying anything. Okay so those neutralize. You
did it בשתיקה *bishitika* והוא כשר *vehu kasher* and if you שחט
*shecht*-ed it בשתיקה *bishitika* it's כשר *kasher*. Now that itself is questionable.
You might remember in the בבלי *Bavli* we had a question whether
פסח בשאר ימות השנה *Pesach bish'ar yemot hashana* בעי עקירה או לא
בעי עקירה *ba'ei akira o lo ba'ei akira*. Does it need to
have its old name uprooted from it which is exactly this question?
If you שחט *shecht* without giving it any כוונה kavana, *kavana* any
designation does it have the old status of פסח *Pesach* and it's
פסול *pasul* or do you actively have to redefine it as something
and you know and you have to actively redefine it to make
it כשר *kasher* or do we say no לא בעי עקירה *lo
ba'ei akira* automatically once it's no longer פסח *Pesach* its identity has
changed? Okay so the question would be what happens if you שחט
*shecht*-ed it בשתיקה *bishitika*? You don't say anything. Is it good or
not? So he's saying לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo* neutralize. It's
like it's בשתיקה *bishitika* and he assumes that בשתיקה *bishitika* is okay.
You don't have to actively change its old name. It automatically is
okay. אמר ליה Amar leh, *amar lei* so he said back to
him אם כן הוא *im kein hu* if you think לשמו ושלא
לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo* is okay אפילו שחטו לשמו על מנת להזות
דמו שלא לשמו *afilu shochto lishma al menat lehazot damo shelo lishma*
even if you somehow separated the לשמו *lishmo* and שלא לשמו *shelo
lishmo*. You שחט *shecht*-ed it לשם פסח *leshem Pesach* with the כוונה
kavana *kavana* to be זורק *zorek* the דם שלא לשמו *dam shelo
lishma*. So according to you why don't we say נעשה משאר שנו
כשחטו לשמו ושלא לשמו בשתיקה ויהא כשר *ya'ase mish'ar shano kishochto lishma
u'shelo lishma bishitika vehei kasher*. Why don't we say that that also
neutralizes and it's כשר *kasher*? And it takes for granted that that
does not. Of course that's a little different because there the שחיטה
*shechita* precedes the זריקה *zrika* and you could say you've already when
the שתיקה shtika *shitika* the the לשמו *lishmo*
takes precedence and defines it as opposed to when they already come
together. But anyway he resisted this idea if you could say they
both are neutralized and even if you somewhat separated it let them
neutralize. אמר רבי אבא מרי *amar Rabbi Abba Mari*
so אבא בר מרי *Abba bar Mari* says מה נאמר בשתיקה *ma
nomar bishitika* what where do you get the idea that if you
did it בשתיקה *bishitika* you take it for granted that it's good?
כשר או נאמר בשתיקה פסול *kasher o nomar bishitika pasul*? We can
say that if you did it בשתיקה *bishitika* it's good we can
say that if you did it בשתיקה *bishitika* it's not good. So
why are you taking for granted that the פסח *Pesach* in the
rest of the year you don't have to actively uproot and change
its name? So again this in the בבלי *Bavli* is a discussion
whether פסח בשאר ימות השנה *Pesach bish'ar yemot hashana* בעי עקירה או
לא בעי עקירה *ba'ei akira o lo ba'ei akira*. Whether it actively
needs its old name to be uprooted and redefined. Here the ירושלמי
*Yerushalmi* is phrasing it as what is its status when it's בשתיקה
*bishitika* when it's silent? So it assumes it's okay and then in
the end you have to like I mean especially after all these
years in the בבלי *Bavli* some of the new formulations of the
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. Who knows what you would say בשתיקה *bishitika*? Maybe you'd
say כשר *kasher* maybe you'd say פסול *pasul*.
Right. שתיקה shtika. *shitika* in the בבלי *Bavli* is so laden with
certain assumptions right? שתיקה כהודאה דמי *shitika kehodaa dami*. Right.
בשתיקה
*bishitika* itself that's true just using the word שתיקה *shitika* as a
powerful word. Yeah it's true but I
was
also pointing about like if you had this question in the בבלי
*Bavli* it would be פסח בשאר ימות השנה בעי עקירה או לא
בעי עקירה תיקו *Pesach bish'ar yemot hashana ba'ei akira o lo ba'ei
akira teiku*, right? And in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* it's מה תאמר בשתיקה
כשר או תאמר בשתיקה פסול *ma tomar bishitika kasher o tomar bishitika
pasul*? You know it's like very interesting to hear the different types
of formulations. Anyway so it doesn't know what the story is if
you
were שתיק *shatik* and
also doesn't know if you said לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo u'shelo lishmo*
whether that neutralized.
No, שתיקה is internal. The question is when you talk about having
particular כוונות, kavanos, whether you have to verbalize it and that we
discussed previously.
It has to be expressed in some way I mean if you're
talking...
Well, that's the exact point. שתיקה's שתיקה. The question is if you
say when you had לשמה lishmo a כוונה, does that mean a
verbalized כוונה and the general assumption is that it does. Okay, now
we get onto the next part, the נזיר. nazir. מותר נזיר לנדבה.
mosar nazir l'nedava. So we're skipping over the נזירים nezirim in the
plural case, an individual נזיר nazir has leftover funds, it goes for
a נדבה. nedava. Similar idea of like leftover for a חטאת. chatas.
רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda amar, והוא שקרבה חטאתו בסוף. v'hu shekarva
chatato besof.
Now by the נזיר nazir it is getting to the idea that
he did not just bring a חטאת. chatas. I don't know why
he didn't get to it by the זבה, zava, but it's getting
to it by the נזיר. nazir. So a נזיר nazir brings an
עולה, olah, שלמים, shelamim, and a חטאת. chatas. So when you have
leftover, leftover from what? I had three hundred dollars, I spent two
hundred of them on the עולה, olah שלמים, shelamim, and the חטאת,
chatas, I had one hundred left over. Is this leftover עולה olah,
money? Is it leftover חטאת chatas money? Leftover שלמים shelamim. money? How
the heck do I know? So it says, ah, what order did
you buy them in? Right, first you buy your עולה, olah, then
you buy your שלמים, shelamim and then you buy your חטאת, chatas,
then the last funds were all going to be for the חטאת
chatas and anything leftover was seen as leftover from the חטאת. chatas.
But if you bought them in a different order, right, first you
bought your חטאת, chatas, then your עולה, olah then your שלמים, shelamim.
then the leftover funds are seen as leftover from the שלמים. shelamim.
Is that clear? So we don't bundle it all together
according to him. והוא שקרבה חטאתו בסוף. v'hu shekarva chatato besof.
That's only if he speaks about offering it at the end, although
the way I just described it almost sort of made more sense
if they whether you bought it at the end, but the way
we look at it is whichever one was offered last, that's the
last one that the funds are seen to have gone to, and
therefore the מותר mosar is the מותר mosar of that קרבן. korban.
אבל אם קרבה שלמים בסוף, aval im karva shelamim besof, but if
the שלמים shelamim was brought at the end, מותר שלמים, mosar shelamim,
the leftover funds go to a שלמים. shelamim, They're seen as leftover
funds from a שלמים. shelamim. אמר רב זירא Amar Rav Zeira no,
אפילו קרבו שלמים לבסוף, afilu karvu shelamim l'besof, even if the שלמים
shelamim is brought at the end, הלכה אחת היא בנזיר, halacha achas
hi benazir, it's one הלכה שתהא מותרן נדבה, shetiheye mosran nedava, that
since there's a חטאת chatas as part of that group of קרבנות,
korbanos, any leftover is considered leftover of a חטאת. chatas. And as
I said, that works well with the earlier discussion also about the
זבה zava that has a חטאת chatas and an עולה olah as
the birds, the leftover funds are seen as leftover חטאת chatas funds.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניתא מסייעא לדין ומתניתא
מסייעא לדין. masnisa mesayeia l'din v'masnisa mesayeia l'din.
We have a ברייתא braisa that supports this one, a ברייתא braisa
supports that one. מתניתא מסייעא לרב זירא, masnisa mesayeia l'Rav Zeira, a
ברייתא braisa that supports Rav Zeira, who said that it's always seen
as leftover חטאת chatas funds. Why? What does the ברייתא braisa say?
אלו
הן מעות סתומות, elu hein maos setumim, the following are undesignated funds,
כל שדמי חטאת מתות מעורבות בהן. kol shedmei chatas mesos meuravas bahen.
So even if you have a חטאת chatas that was able basically
the owner died and it couldn't be brought, so essentially it's considered
now מותר חטאת, mosar chatas, right, the funds are left over. It's
mixed up in them, then it's all considered, again, the phrase of
מעות סתומות, maos setumim, but it means in this context it means
that the leftover funds would go for the נדבה. nedava. The חידוש
chiddush is the last part of it. That's when the funds have
not even been separated out. But then the חידוש chiddush is, ואפילו
הפריש דמי חטאת מתוכן מעות סתומות הן. va'afilu hifrish dmei chatas mitokhan
maos setumim hein. Meaning, somebody set aside like three hundred dollars. He
took out, and I'm going to use all this for my נזיר,
nazir, for my קרבנות korbanos amongst which is a חטאת chatas and
an עולה olah, and who knows what else. Okay, then he took
aside one hundred dollars and said, "Good, this is going to be
the חטאת chatas money." And then he dropped dead. Okay, so this
is all now leftover funds. Since this pile originally had חטאת chatas
money in it, even though the חטאת chatas money has been removed,
this pile is considered to be leftover חטאת chatas funds and therefore
goes לנדבה l'nedava and not for עולה, olah not for שלמים, shelamim.
not for any of that. So that's exactly like the נזיר. nazir.
Here too, you had money for your נזיר nazir קרבן, korban, even
whatever order you bought them in, whatever order they were offered, since
חטאת chatas funds were part of that originally, any extra is considered
extra חטאת. chatas.
It's the מחשבה, machshava, the מעיקרא me'ikara is קובע. kovaia.
Well, but it's also הקדש. hektesh. It's not just מחשבה. machshava. You're
מקדיש makdish the funds as well. So but then the identity remains
always as part of this group. Okay, מתניתא מסייעא לרב חסדא, masnisa
mesayeia l'Rav Chisda, the following ברייתא braisa supports Rav Chisda. אלו לחטאתי,
elu l'chatasi, if somebody says "the following will be for my חטאת",
chatas והשאר לשאר נזירותי, v'hashar lishar nezirusai,
"and the rest is for the rest of my other קרבנות korbanos
as a נזיר", nazir ומת, umes, and then the guy dropped dead.
מועלין בכולן ואין מועלין במקצתן. moalin b'kulan v'ein moalin b'miktzasan.
Now of course that's a funny phrase. You can do מעילה me'ilah
with all of them but not with some of them. But what
it means is not that you're allowed to, if you use all
of the funds you've done מעילה, me'ilah, if you've used only some
of the funds you do not. Why? You cannot do
מעילה me'ilah with a
שלמים. shelamim So basically what you see that you've got here in
this pile is a mixture of שלמים shelamim, funds and עולה olah,
funds. So if you use all the money you've done מעילה, me'ilah,
some of those funds are for an עולה, olah but if you've
only used some of the money we can't tag you with מעילה
me'ilah because maybe those are the funds that would have gone to
a שלמים. shelamim All right now, how that actually ואין מועלין במקצתן.
v'ein moilin bimiktzatan. ולא אמר v'lo amar אם מת יפלו לנדבה, im
meis yiplu l'nidavah, and it does not say in that ברייתא, braisa,
it's almost like an argument from silence that if the guy died
then the money gets used for a נדבה, nidavah, and presumably and
you could also just say by the fact that it looks at
the funds as being a mixture of עולה olah, and שלמים shelamim,
and so on, presumably it does not say since חטאת chatas was
once part of it that always stamps its identity. Okay, so that's
a little more of an argument of silence but we see that
according to that it does not give that example that the funds
would always be going to נדבה nidavah if the person died. Okay.
So רב חסדא אמר: Rav Chisda amar: מותר לחמו של נזיר. mosar
lachmo shel Nazir.
So that was talking about that whole package of חטאת, chatas, עולה,
olah, שלמים, shelamim, is it always stamped with the חטאת chatas identity.
Now we talk about the other parts of a נזיר. Nazir. מותר
לחמו של נזיר. mosar lachmo shel Nazir. In other words, a נזיר
Nazir would bring with his קרבן korban certain loaves of bread and
you say he set aside money specifically for those loaves and there
was leftover money. So what do we do with it? ירקב, yirkav,
you have to let them rot. Sort of like the גמרא Gemara
said before about throwing it in the ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. Certain
types of obligations that are not חטאת chatas related, again maybe the
עולה, ola חטאת, chatas, ושלמים v'shelamim are all package but they're all
animal קרבנות korbanos so they're seen as getting the חטאת chatas identity.
But certain obligations that are not חטאת chatas related they don't go
לנדבה. l'nidavah. So what do you do? Throw it into the sea,
sort of like what it said before about the כהן גדול's Kohen
Gadol עשירית האיפה. Asiris HaEifah. It's interesting that they're both by the
way מנחה mincha types of you know flour types of things. I'm
not sure if that's significant. Yeah.
Sorry, this is you actually had the physical bread here?
Well the phrase ירקב yirkav sounds like physical bread but maybe you
bought a lot of flour. If it was other money you would
just throw it you know throw it in the ים המלח Yam
HaMelach or something. Or maybe you bought a lot of flour and
then you had leftover dough. So then even that would be ירקב.
yirkav. But let's take a look. But it seems that we're not
just talking about that. We're talking about funds as well because the
גמרא Gemara considers other possibilities. אמר רבי יוסי: Amar Rabbi Yose: ויאות.
v'ya'os. Is that really correct? Oh no, ויאות, v'ya'os, that is correct.
Sometimes hard to tell between statement or question. That is correct. וכן
הוא. v'chein hu. להקריבו בפני עצמו
l'hakrivo bifnei
atzmo אי אתה יכול ein atah yachol שאין לך לחם קרב לעצמו.
she'ein l'cha lechem kareiv l'atzmo. To bring it by itself, like to
say in you know מותר שלמים שלמים, mosar shelamim shelamim, מותר עולה
עולה. mosar olah olah. So why does it say מותר לחם לחם?
mosar lechem lechem? No, we don't have that type of an independent
קרבן. korban.
We don't have a מנחה.
mincha. Yeah, but it's exactly a, it's not just סתם מנחה stam
mincha meaning it's or maybe it's the specific type of לחם. lechem.
But I don't think it's a סתם מנחה. stam mincha. You bring
it as what does it say that you bring for the נזיר?
Nazir? Let's take a look at the פסוק. pasuk.
Really tests your knowledge here. Hold on. Yes. וסל מצות סלת חלות
בלולת
בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן
ומנחתם ונסכיהם. V'sal matzos soles chalos belulos
bashamen u'rekikei matzos meshuchim
bashamen u'minchasam v'niskeihem.
I don't
know,
would this be done the same way a מנחה mincha was done?
I mean it's also here you're not מקריב makriv a you know
a what do you call it
a קומץ. kometz. You just do a whole ritual with waving it.
So maybe it means that type of a קרבן korban doesn't go
by itself. You can't bring the same type. Meaning you can't say
like שלמים שלמים. shelamim shelamim. You can't say you know, again we're
not even talking about bread, we're talking about money. So it's not
the thing, so you can't bring use the money for this type
of an offering of bread. That this type of an offering of
bread does not exist by itself.
Can't just use it
for any kind of bread? Well no, well what about if you're
using it for something else? Why you know why limit yourself to
a מנחה? mincha? Bring any קרבן. korban. The fact that it's bread
is significant. We don't say oh if it was an animal use
it for some other animal קרבן, korban, right? It's the specific way
in which it's brought. So it says to use it for the
same type of לחם lechem קרבן korban that doesn't happen by itself.
להקריבו עם נזירות אחרת? L'hakrivo im nezirus acheres? How about saving the
funds for more for another time you're a נזיר? Nazir? I mean
a guy who's a נזיר Nazir once will probably be a נזיר
Nazir again. So anyway, אי אתה יכול ein atah yachol שאין לך
נזירות בלא לחם. she'ein l'cha nezirus belo lechem.
Because your other נזירות nezirus will require its own sanctification of לחם,
lechem, not using funds that were designated for something else. Every נזירות
nezirus needs its own sanctification for the bread. So therefore, לפום כן,
l'fum kein, you can't use it for related for its exact purpose
or for a related purpose. צריכא למימר: Tzaricha l'meimar: מותר לחמו של
נזיר ירקב. mosar lachmo shel Nazir yirkav. You have to let it
rot. So again, this idea... that if it's a, if it's can't,
you know, if it's not a חטאת chatas status, a חטאת chatas
can become a נדבה. nedava. שלמים shelamim שלמים, עולה ola, עולה, ola,
חטאת chatas נדבה, nedava, this sort of falls between the cracks, can't
become the same thing, can't be used for a related thing, therefore
you have to just let it rot. Okay. So אמר רב יוסף
Amar Rav Yosef סברינה מימר savrina meimar
we thought to say that הוא לחמו הוא מותר נסכיו hu lachmo
hu motar niscav the same way you would say this that the
bread has to be let rot, money set aside for the wine
that's brought for the נזיר nazir would also have to have to
have to let rot if you had leftover money for the same
reason. You can't bring it by itself and you can't bring it
with another נזיר nazir קרבן. korban. So אמר רב יוסי בר רבי
בון Amar Rav Yossi bar Rabbi Bun no, מותר נסכיו קדשי קדשים
אינון ויפלו לנדבה motar niscav kodshei kodashim inun v'yiplu l'nedava
and now we get this issue about it's not limited to a
חטאת. chatas. The נסכים nesachim have this קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim status,
right? They're just poured on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, they're not eaten and
so on. And therefore, it's not just that a חטאת chatas can
become a נדבה, nedava, it's that קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim can become
a נדבה. nedava. So that allows us again, this question of exactly
what has this rule that if you can't, you know, use it,
let it just be a נדבה nedava is not clear. I'll remind
you what we said so far. שקלים shkalim can become a נדבה,
nedava, right? That's not a חטאת. chatas. You know, it's generally brought
for an עולה, ola, the general קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur עולה, ola,
so maybe here it could be used like this idea קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. But okay, שקלים. shkalim. We mentioned the זבה, zava, the
זבה zava whose קרבן korban is both a חטאת chatas and an
עולה, ola but maybe that's because it's part of a bundle. We
have the discussion about the מנחה mincha of the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol which was debated whether that was נדבה nedava or not. So
that's not a חטאת, chatas, but that's also קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim,
right? And now we had this... so this is the question about
is it just a חטאת, chatas, you know, or is it some
broader category? Certainly שקלים shkalim is not a חטאת chatas and that's
in this category of מותר לנדבה. motar l'nedava.
All חטאות chataos are קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, correct? Yes. So here
the question just simply is maybe it's just all...
right, maybe it's not limited to... right, right. Okay. No, but not
all קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim because an עולה ola. is קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim and then you get to reuse it for an עולה.
ola So it's when it's a קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim that you
don't have something to do with the funds. It's not clear how
you can reuse the funds, then maybe it can be for a
נדבה. nedava.
Also, you said something about the שלמים, if I designate an animal
for שלמים and then I take the fleece and I weave something
with it, make a sweater, that's not מעילה? me'ilah?
Correct. It's not מותר mutar but it's not מעילה me'ilah because it's
not קדשי ה'. kodshei Hashem. Okay, מזבח ה', mizbe'ach Hashem, okay. So
okay,
אל צד al tzad ויפלו
לנדבה. v'yiplu l'nedava. על דעתיה דרבי יוסי בר רבי בון, Al dateih
de'Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Bun, so according to the opinion of Rabbi
Yossi bar Rabbi Bun that basically says that this becomes a נדבה,
nedava, קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, שמואל אליבא דרב חסדא Shmuel aliba de'Rav
Chisda במותר נסכיו, bemotar niscav, now it's very hard to read this
but or whatever, but שמואל, Shmuel remember שמואל Shmuel we said before
was about the הפריש שקליו ומת יפלו לנדבה, hifrish shkalov u'meis yiplu
l'nedava, right? So we're going to line up a couple of people
that have this similar idea that קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim money gets
to become a נדבה. nedava. So שמואל אליבא דרב חסדא במותר נסכיו
ורבי חייא ורבי אלעזר שלשתן אמרו דבר אחד. Shmuel aliba de'Rav Chisda
bemotar niscav v'Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Elazar shloshtan amru davar echad. Okay, let's
just... these three said one thing. Let's sort of see what it
says they said and then we'll worry about how it exactly what
it said about you
know how
it presented their names in the... So these three said one thing.
רבי חייא אהא דאמרין, Rabbi Chiya aha d'amrin, Rabbi Chiya what we
said, because what did Rabbi Chiya say, of course you see there's
a question whether it's חסדא Chisda or חייא, Chiya, okay, but רבי
חייא, Rabbi Chiya, שמואל דאמר רבי יוסי אהא דתמן חמי חברייא דרב
יהודה שאיל לשמואל הפריש שקליו ומת אמר ליה יפלו לנדבה. Shmuel d'amar
Rabbi Yossi aha d'taman chami chevrayya de'Rav Yehuda sha'il le'Shmuel hifrish shkalov
u'meis amar leih yiplu l'nedava. So the שקל shekel becomes a נדבה.
nedava. רבי אלעזר אומר מותר עשירית האיפה שלו, Rabbi Elazar omer motar
asiris ha'eifah shelo, רבי יוחנן אומר יוליכם לים המלח, Rabbi Yochanan omer
yolichem l'Yam HaMelach, רבי אלעזר אומר יפלו לנדבה. Rabbi Elazar omer yiplu
l'nedava. So so you see this Rabbi Elazar says leftover not חטאת,
chatas, it's קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, it becomes a נדבה. nedava. שמואל
says the שקל shekel becomes a נדבה, nedava, also not a חטאת.
chatas. So
those Rabbi Elazar and Shmuel said the same thing. Now the question
is what did it mean here about this line about רבי חייא
רבי חסדא אהא דאמרין Rabbi Chiya Rabbi Chisda aha d'amrin because what
did Rabbi Chiya and what did Rabbi Chisda say? רב חסדא Rav
Chisda was the one that said מותר לחמו ירקב. motar lachmo yirkav.
So שמואל אליבא דרב חסדא Shmuel aliba de'Rav Chisda במותר נסכיו bemotar
niscav ורבי חייא ורבי אלעזר שלשתן אמרו דבר אחד. v'Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi
Elazar shloshtan amru davar echad. Now the question is what did it
mean here about this line about רבי חייא רבי חסדא אהא דאמרין
Rabbi Chiya Rabbi Chisda aha d'amrin because what did Rabbi Chiya and
what did Rabbi Chisda say? רב חסדא Rav Chisda said this whole
thing about the חטאת chatas and the עולה being mixed together by
the נזיר, nazir, that's not where... or here he said מותר לחמו
של נזיר ירקב. motar lachmo shel nazir yirkav. So it's actually the
opposite. He could have said the extra לחם lechem although that's not...
Oh, I see. No, here's the point. Here's the point. Since רב
חסדא Rav Chisda said the leftover money of a נזיר *Nazir*'s לחם
*Lechem* is יוקחו *Yukchu*, presumably he emphasized לחם *Lechem* as distinct from
נסכים *Nisachim*. And the נסכים *Nisachim* would not be יוקחו *Yukchu* because
the נסכים *Nisachim* is קדשי קדשים *Kodshei Kodashim*. And therefore it would
be לנדבה *li-Nedavah*. So let's read that again, okay? So I'm just
going to read that one more time just to be clear. Just
like this: על דעתיה דרבי יוסי ברבי בון *Al daitei d'Rebbi Yose
bar Rebbi Bun*, right now I got it, על דעתיה דרבי יוסי
ברבי בון *Al daitei d'Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi Bun*, רבי יוסי ברבי
בון *Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi Bun* explains רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*, that
רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* said his הלכה *halacha* only by the bread,
but that רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* would say that by the נסכים
*Nisachim*, because it's קדשי קדשים *Kodshei Kodashim*, it would be for an
עולה *Olah*. So according to his interpretation of רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*,
we can say the following thing. We can say the following thing:
שמואל *Shmuel*, number one, על דעתיה דרב חסדא *Al daitei d'Rav Chisda*,
the מותר נסכים *mosar nisachim* really belongs earlier. Should be, right, should
be: על דעתיה דרבי יוסי ברבי בון *Al daitei d'Rebbi Yose bar
Rebbi Bun* according to how he's interpreted what רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*
said by the מותר נסכים *mosar nisachim* that they become a, that
they become a נדבה nedavah *nedavah*. So according to him, שמואל, רב
חסדא, ורבי אליעזר, שלושתן אמרו דבר אחד *Shmuel, Rav Chisda, v'Rebbi Eliezer,
shloshtan amru davar echad*. Those three all said one thing. Right? רב
חסדא *Rav Chisda*, it should be רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* not רב
חייא *Rav Chiya*, הא דאמרין *ha de-amrin*. רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* what
we said, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* said his הלכה *halacha* only by
the bread, but the נסכים *Nisachim* would become a נדבה *nedavah* because
it's קדשי קדשים *Kodshei Kodashim*. רבי יהודה בשם שמואל *Rebbi Yehuda be-shem
Shmuel* by the שקלים *shkalim*. And this הלכה *halacha* by the חבתי
טפיא *chavitei tipeya* according to רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer* also by it.
All right, did you get that more or less, or did I
totally confuse you? I think I confused myself.
תוספות *Tosafot* says something different.
Okay, but the basic point is like this: According to רבי יוסי
ברבי בון *Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi Bun*, he explained רב חסדא *Rav
Chisda*'s point about the bread of the נזיר *Nazir* that it's רק
*rak*, that's only by bread because it's קדשי קלים *Kodshei Kalim* and
we can't do anything with it. But he says that according to
רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*, by the wine of the נזיר *Nazir*, that
would actually get to be used as a נדבה *nedavah*. So what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying, according to his reading of רב חסדא
*Rav Chisda*, we have three opinions that say that leftover קדשי קדשים
*Kodshei Kodashim* is נדבה *nedavah*: This reading by the נזיר *Nazir*, what
שמואל *Shmuel* said by the שקל *shekel*, and the opinion by the
כהן חבתי טפיא *kohen chavitei tipeya* that that gets to be used
as a נדבה *nedavah* as well. Okay, is everybody thoroughly confused? Let's
take a look now at the next משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. מותר שבויים
לשבויים *Mosar shvuyim li-shvuyim*. Now this becomes fascinating because in a number
of places the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, you see
the בבלי *Bavli* and the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, treat money that's designated for
מצוה *mitzvah* purposes like צדקה *tzedakah* and so on to be somewhat
analogous to money that's been sanctified and הקדש *hekdesh*. And the question
of, ask, can you reuse it for other types of purposes? So
that's what this משנה Mishna *Mishnah* turns to. If you have money
collected for פדיון שבויים *pidyon shvuyim* for שבויים *shvuyim*, you save it
for, God forbid, and we'll have another need for redeeming captives. מותר
שבוי shavuy? לאותו שבוי *Mosar shavuy l'oto shavuy*. If you raised money
for a particular captive and then there was leftover money after he
was redeemed, then it goes to him.
He gets to pocket it.
Oh, no, it was made for him.
Taking him captive again? No, that's what I thought.
No, I hope not. No. מותר עניים לעניים *Mosar aniyim l'aniyim*.
Left money collected
for עניים *aniyim* generically, extra money gets saved for future עניים *aniyim*.
מותר עני *Mosar ani*, if it's money collected for a particular poor
person, "Hey, this guy lost his house, let's raise money, let's buy
the house back from the bank," for a particular purpose and then
you collected more money than you expected, then לאותו עני *l'oto ani*,
he gets it. מותר המתים למתים *Mosar hametim lametim*. Money collected generally
for the purpose of burying the dead, any leftover funds get saved
for that purpose. מותר המת *Mosar hamet*, but if it was money
collected for a particular dead person to bury him and you collected
more money than you were expecting, ליורשיו *l'yorshav*, then it goes to
the heirs. רבי מאיר אומר *Rebbi Meir omer*, no, מותר המת יהא
מונח עד שיבוא אליהו *Mosar hamet yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu*. I
don't know whether to use the money for doing something nicer for
the dead person or to give it to the heirs, so you
have to just put it in escrow. רבי נתן Rabbi Natan, אומר
*Rebbi Natan omer*, all right, we'll see what רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
*Rebbi Natan* says, מותר המת בונין לו נפש על קברו *Mosar hamet
bonin lo nefesh al kivro*. No, actually, he's the other extreme. He
says you use the leftover money, you buy a nice tombstone, you
use, so even though there was enough money, you only raised the
money to buy the burial plot and the burial, if there's leftover
money do something else for the מת meit *met*. So the question
here why the מת meit. *met* might be different is as opposed
to the case by the עני *ani* or the שבוי *shavuy*, they're
alive. If they want to give it to somebody else, that's their
choice. Here the מת meit. *met* you can't ask. So fundamentally you
would say it follows the rule that it goes to the מת
meit *met*, but maybe the מת meit *met*, then the question is,
would you assume implicitly the מת *met* would rather his heirs just
keep the extra money, or we would assume that the מת *met*
would want actually, if you raised it for him, to do something
nicer for his grave? So here's the question. Or he would want
it for charity, how do you know? All right, okay, that's true
too. But I guess there's an assumption that it sort of starts
within, you know, because what would happen if the מת *met* got
it while he was alive and then he died? Then it would
pass on to his heirs. So it does still follow that idea
that it goes to the person you raised it for, but here
you don't exactly know what to do in the case of a
מת *met*. Let's look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. גבו לו בחזקת
שאין לו ונמצא שיש לו Gavlu lo be-chezkat she-ein lo ve-nimtza she-yesh
lo *Gavu lo be-chezkas she-ein lo v'nimtza she-yesh lo*. Let's say you
collected money for, for somebody and you thought, for the מת *met*,
and we thought that there, you know, we thought that this guy
was a pauper, we raised money to buy a burial plot... And
then you find out that it looked like he actually had all
of his money buried away, squirreled away in his mattress, and he
didn't mislead you, and he doesn't need our money. So what's the
הלכה with this money? Do we say מותר המת ליורשיו motar ha-meit
le-yorshav or do we say the whole thing was a טעות ta'os
and you give it back to the people you collected it for?
גבו לו בחזקת שאין לו ונמצא שיש לו for the מת it's
assumed... yeah, okay, it's assumed for the מת. רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah
סבר מימר savar meimar מותר המת ליורשיו. motar ha-meit le-yorshav. Oh, he
thought to say let's give it to the יורשים. yorshim. You know,
it doesn't matter, it was raised for him. ענה ליה Ana leh
רב אידי, Rav Idi, רב אידי דחוטרא Rav Idi de-Chutra from this
place חוטרא Chutra said to him,
הגא עצמך דלא כיון אלא ליה. Haga atzmecha de-lo kivein ela leh.
They only did it, intended to do it, because they thought he
needed it. So as opposed to the other case he really did
need it, it was left over; here they thought he needed it
and he didn't. The whole thing was a טעות. ta'os. So אמר
ליה, Amar leh, he said back to him, he maybe didn't like
the sort of tone that this rabbi used presumably anyway, just הגא
עצמך Haga atzmecha and so on. So he said back to him
אמר ליה, amar lei אנא לא אמרי את מנא לך? Ana lo
amari at mena lach? Hey, I didn't say that idea, where do
you think you got that idea from?
Meaning like, who died and made you king? Yeah, you say so...
let's hear whatever. It's a סברא. sevara. What makes you think that's
right? It's not my סברא. sevara. So what makes you think that's
the right סברא? sevara?
All right, responsibility for the סברא.
sevara. Anyway, but you do hear the point and that's why the
גמרא asks the question that that is fundamentally different.
To an extent more than a נדבה as opposed to...
we gotta get going first. Okay, so the גמרא says like this,
תני בשם רבי נתן, Tani be-shem Rabbi Natan, which we taught a
ברייתא braita in the name of רבי נתן, מותר המת יבנה לו
נפש על קברו. Motar ha-meit yibaneh lo nefesh al kivro. So if
you have leftover money, this is like the position of רבי נתן
at the end of our משנה, so here's a ברייתא braita following
that. Leftover money you build a like a tombstone on his grave
site. ויעשה לו זילוף על גבי מיטתו, Ve-ya'aseh lo ziluf al gabei
mitato, and you also use some money for some sprinkling of wine
when you're carrying out the ביר beer when you're carrying out the
coffin. You know, it's rotting a little, they didn't have refrigeration, what
they would do is they'd sprinkle wine so it wouldn't smell. So
you could also use money for that as well. That's extra things
you can do with the money and you should use it for
the מת. תני, Tani, אין פודין שבוי בשבוי. Ein podin shavuy be-shavuy.
You do not redeem one captive with enough from money for another
captive. If you raise money for one captive you don't transfer it
for another one, which is pretty much what the משנה sounds like.
ואין גובין טלית בטלית. Ve-ein govin tallit be-tallit. This is
interesting. If you don't collect a טלית tallit for a טלית, tallit,
which is very strange. I mean the מפרשים meforshim say that it
means that if you were collecting money like for a טלית וציצית
tallit ve-tzitzis and then you wanted to buy a nicer one you
don't switch it, which is a... I'm sorry, yeah, which is a
little bit strange,
because like, you know, what is the idea of setting aside money
for a... anyway טלית tallit in the גמרא does not really mean
טלית tallit for ציצית. tzitzis. It really means like a cloak. And
the phrase is גובין, govin, so you don't sort of גובין govin
is like you collect a טלית. tallit. So what that means you
don't collect a טלית tallit for a טלית tallit I really don't
know exactly. Anyway, some of the מפרשים say it means money set
aside to buy one type of a טלית tallit with ציצית, tzitzis,
you don't say, oh, here's a nicer one and you switch. ואין
ממחין ביד פרנסין לכך. Ve-ein memachin be-yad parnasin le-kach. However, there's a
difference between individuals collecting a fund and the charity officers. The charity
officers are allowed to switch where their funds are designated because basically
when you give it to them you give it to them with
an understanding of that they have discretion. So if you're doing your
own collecting and it's for a specific person it's locked into that
person. For them though, even though there might be a general goal,
there's understanding for specific person? Yes, so that's not exactly clear, like
what if they say, we are collecting for this שבוי? So the
lines here are not exactly clear. I want to read one following
thing getting back to the מת and the tombstone. So תני, Tani,
we turn the ברייתא, braita, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, אין עושין נפשות לצדיקים. Ein osin nefashot la-tzaddikim. You
don't make tombstones for the righteous. דבריהם הן הן זכרונם. Divreihem hen
hen zichronam. For them, there's a very famous phrase, beautiful phrase, their
teachings, what they left behind, their legacy, should be their thing. You
don't make, you don't make... maybe also they didn't want this whole
thing of worshipping the graves of the צדיקים, tzaddikim, I don't know,
but basically, you know, it's not about physical things, it's about their
legacy. You know, Woody Allen once said, he said, I don't want
to become immortal through my works, I want to become immortal by
not dying. That's right.
Anyway, but for the מת דבריהם הן הן זכרונם. Divreihem hen hen
zichronam. I understand. רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, now let's start, I want
to start a little story which we'll finish tomorrow. רבי יוחנן הוה
מסמך ואזל. Rabbi Yochanan hava masmach ve-azal. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
being supported and going, because he was heavy he needed to be
supported by... and he was...
and he was supporting himself on רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba. וחזייה רבי אלעזר. Ve-chazyei Rabbi Elazar. Now רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar saw רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. He was from בבל Bavel and
he had come to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ומיטמר ליה מקמיה. U-mitmar
leh mi-kamei. And when he saw רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan coming he
went and he hid. Okay, because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was going
slowly, he came on the other side of the street, he saw
him and he went and he went and he went and to
hide. ומיטמר ליה מקמיה. U-mitmar leh mi-kamei. ואמר, Ve-amar, now רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said. Now Rabbi Chiya bar Abba who was supporting him,
הני תרתי מיליי הדין בבלאה עבד בי. hani tarti milayu hadein Bavla
avad bi. So this Babylonian did two things to me, בי bi
he sort of refers to himself in the third person, he says
to him but he means to me. He offended me doubly. How
did he offend me doubly?
חדא דלא שאל בשלומי, chada d'lo sha'al bishlomei, the one is he
didn't ask after my wellbeing, he didn't say שלום עליך רבי מורי.
shalom alecha rabbi mori. וחדא דמיטמר, v'chada d'mitmar, and number two is
he went into hiding like he doesn't even want to see me.
אמר ליה amar lei Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, so Rabbi Yaakov bar
Idi who happened to be there said to him, כך מנהגין גבהון,
kach minhagin gav'hon, that's how they practice over there. Quite fascinating in
just these two amudim we have a lot of reference to בבל.
Bavel. Okay, this Babylonian, I heard over there, I heard the voice
of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, and so here
he says that's what they practice over there. דזעירא לא שאל בשלומיה
דרבה, d'zeira lo sha'al bishlomeih d'rabba, a young one or a smaller
person, a smaller stature doesn't ask after the wellbeing of somebody of
greater stature. זוטרא? zutra? So we're going to get to that. Okay,
so that he didn't say shalom alecha, it was not seen as
respectful for him to ask after you. Okay, that's what you do
with a friend, not what you do with a rebbi. So that's
how the Babylonians do it.
So therefore, and therefore ואינון נהיגין ומקיימין, v'inu nahigin u'mekaymin, they practice
and fulfill the following verse, ראוני נערים ונחבאו, re'uni ne'arim venichba'u, the
young ones see me and they go and they hide, וישישים קמו
עמדו, veyshishim kamu amadu, and the old ones get up and stand.
So maybe it seemed like they're so afraid of you, you know,
so much awe and respect that they that they that they
can't even encounter you, they don't ask after your wellbeing. That's what
you do if you're a friend. This actually is a showing of
awe and respect and reverence. So אמר להו, amar lehu, now he
wanted to almost, he asked him like a fake question to get
him to, you know, to get him somewhere. So this whoever was
it,
Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi said to Rabbi Yochanan,
so אמר ליה amar lei, it should be, מהו מיעבר קמי דהדין
צלמיא? mahu me'avar kamei d'hadein tzalmaya? Am I allowed to walk in
front of this particular item? Okay, so he asked Rabbi Yochanan, is
it muttar for me to walk in front of this idol? אמר
ליה, amar lei, מה פליג ליה יקר? ma palig lei y'kar? What
what are you doing showing it honor that you treat it in
so much awe that you won't walk in front of it? No,
עבור קמוהי וסמי עינך, avor kumei v'samei eynech, walk in front of
it and close your eyes. Don't treat it like Voldemort, right? If
you can't say the name of
something you show whatever its significance, right? So it's sort of like,
oh my god, I'm not going to walk in front of that
idol. That shows it that shows it reverence and significance. Show it
disrespect, walk in front of it and close your eyes. So אמר
ליה, so then he said back to him to Rabbi Yochanan, אה,
יאות רבי אליעזר עבד, ah, ya'os Rabbi Eliezer avad, you see
Rabbi Eliezer did right? Because since he can't ask your respect, because
that's their practice, ask ask after your wellbeing, so to pass in
front of you and not say anything would be the biggest sign
of disrespect. And it actually shows respect if he's not prepared to
walk in front of you.
Okay, דלא עבר קמך, d'lo avar kamach, so you see he did
right. So now we're going to find out tomorrow that Rabbi Yochanan
is not done with his טענות, tainos, he has other reasons he's
upset about and we will continue this interesting...
alright.